<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Terminal | AndSt</title>
    <link>https://andst.github.io/tag/terminal/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://andst.github.io/tag/terminal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Terminal</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://andst.github.io/media/icon_huf55df3efd36cb4bdb6539523da3e6974_26772_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Terminal</title>
      <link>https://andst.github.io/tag/terminal/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Terminal Setup</title>
      <link>https://andst.github.io/post/terminal_setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andst.github.io/post/terminal_setup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within this post I want to talk about my terminal tooling.
For me, the terminal is of my most important tools, probably the most important tool.
I use it to set up my programming environments, configure everything, start programs and handle and view data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my setup on this Github Repo: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/AndSt/zsh-config&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://github.com/AndSt/zsh-config&lt;/a&gt;. I also use this directory to work on remote machine. In that way I can quickly setup new systems. As I want to make it compatible with Linux and Mac I&amp;rsquo;m still not fully happy. Recommendations are welcome! Right now I have two scripts, one for each system, installing programs such as VLC, Google Chrome and performing update commands such as apt upgrade. Afterwards I use VCSH combine with myrepos to set up my system. I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://pikedom.com/managing-dot-files-with-vcsh-and-myrepo/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; guide to distribute the setup in the repo mentioned above to new systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly I use ZSH. Using it provided me with a huge productivity boost.
I like to keep my home directory tidy, so I use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/XDG_Base_Directory&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;XDG Base Directory specification&lt;/a&gt; to structure my home directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;python-setup&#34;&gt;Python Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since about 2.5 years Python is main programming language. On this note, I should note that I&amp;rsquo;m really happy and enjoy it to work with this language.
Logically a big part of my setup is built for programming with Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use virtualenv in combination with &lt;a href=&#34;https://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/a&gt; to work on different projects. I favour it over other Python environment systems such as Anaconda as it is low level and easier compatible with pip. Surely there are other good choices, but so far it has met all my needs and there is no need to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally I built some scripts to work with environments. For instance I built a command called &amp;ldquo;cvenv&amp;rdquo; which creates a new environment and installs some libraries I need in all my projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ohmyzsh/ohmyzsh/tree/master/plugins/virtualenvwrapper&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/a&gt; ZSH plugin. If a project repository is named like an existing environment, the plugin automically enters it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;plugins&#34;&gt;Plugins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After googling and adding and removing some, I ended up using these plugins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git: Some git visualizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;zsh-autosuggestions: Suggests previous commands in light gray&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;virtualenvwrapper: Automatically enter python environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;autojump: Learning system to jump to different parts of the system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dotenv: If a .env file is present in a directory, it is automatically sourced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;zsh-syntax-highlighting: Beautifies terminal output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s really a lot of plugins. Go &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ohmyzsh/ohmyzsh/tree/master/plugins&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to find them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;awesome-reads&#34;&gt;Awesome reads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/unixorn/awesome-dotfiles&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Awesome Dotfiles:&lt;/a&gt; Another awesome library. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested to know more about Dotfiles, this should be a good entry point to find interesting resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
